Okay, בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*. Today's דף daf *daf* is דף daf,
ז׳ *daf zayin*, and we pick up at the bottom of ו׳
עמוד ב׳ *vav amud bet*. And the discussion here is, and we've
been dealing with different sources for בל תאחר bal teachar, *bal t'acher*
and also recently the positions of Rava that extended it, extended it,
צדקה tzedakah. *tzedakah* you're over לאלתר *l'alter* right away when the עניים
aniyim *aniyim* are present,
you're מבטל דעשה *mevatel de'asei* even after the first רגל regel. *regel*,
you're over every single minute after you've transgressed and related issues. Okay,
so now, and then we also had the idea that you would
also be over after a year even before שלוש רגלים shalosh regalim?
*shalosh regalim*, and we had scenarios in which that could happen. Now
we pick up at the bottom of ו׳ עמוד ב׳ *vav amud
bet*, and we have the following: בעי רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira,
*Bay Rabbi Zeira*, about 15 lines from the bottom right after the
asterisk where it says חמישה *chamisha*. So let's just get started for
a minute and then we'll ask. בעי רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira *Bay
Rabbi Zeira*, יורש מהו בבל Bavel תאחר *yoresh mahu b'bal t'acher*? Does
the יורש *yoresh* transgress בל תאחר bal teachar. *bal t'acher*? The heir,
because the הלכה halacha *halacha* is is that if a person's father
or whatever, mother, let's say father, you know, took a vow and
separated off an animal, if they just took a personal vow it
doesn't transfer to you, but they sanctified an animal and then this
person, the heir, inherited it, he has to bring it. So does
he have בל תאחר bal teachar *bal t'acher*? Now on the one
hand you might say, well he didn't take the vow, but as
we've already learned בל תאחר bal teachar. *bal t'acher* is not limited
to vows because בל תאחר bal teachar *bal t'acher* is even if
somebody has an obligation to bring a חטאת *chatas* or an אשם
*asham*, so it's an obligation of a קרבן korban *korban* even without
it being a vow. Okay, although this is a little bit different
because this is also
the animal is sanctified but you don't have a personal obligation, right?
The obligation stems from the fact that you've inherited an עולה olah
*olah*, but it's not like A, you didn't take a vow, you
didn't sanctify it, and B, it's not like a חטאת *chatas* or
an אשם *asham* where you're obligated, right? I mean you're not obligated,
it doesn't start by an obligation on you the person, it starts
by a reality that you have a sanctified animal in your house.
So you know, so this is, so it's obviously a slightly, it's
a different case than the classic בל תאחר bal teachar. *bal t'acher*.
So חטאת *chatas* anyway?
What? You inherited a חטאת *chatas*, right?
Yeah,
okay, but we're not talking about that, that's a story. So what
is the story with the יורש *yoresh* with בל תאחר bal teachar
*bal t'acher*? You didn't take the vow, you don't have a direct
personal obligation, but you are obligated to bring it because it is
your sanctified animal, a sanctified animal that you inherited. So מהו בבל
Bavel. תאחר *mahu b'bal t'acher*? כי תדור נדר neder, לה׳ אלוקיך *Ki
tidor neder la'Hashem Elokecha*, the רחמנא *Rachmana* says if you make a
vow, והא לא נדר *ve-ha lo nadar*, and he did not make
a vow. Although as I pointed out there is בל תאחר bal
ta'acher *bal t'acher* without having made a vow. But nevertheless, it didn't
start with you. או דלמא *O dilma*, ובאת שמה והבאת שמה *u'vashta
shama v'heveisa shama*, you should bring there, you should come there and
bring there to ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash,
*Beis Hamikdash* your קרבנות korbanos. *korbanot*, and you're obligated. Now that's not
a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* in בל תאחר bal ta'acher *bal t'acher*, that's
a general פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* about bringing your קרבנות korbanos *korbanot* to
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beis Hamikdash*, but maybe they're linked and
maybe if you have any obligation to bring a קרבן korban, *korban*
even if it got to you through inheriting this animal, it would
also link you to בל תאחר bal ta'acher, *bal t'acher*. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says תא שמע *T'shema*, come and hear, דתני רבי
חייא *detani Rabbi Chiya*, מעמך *me'imach*, כי דרוש ידרשנו ה׳ אלוקיך מעמך
*ki dorosh yidreshenu Hashem Elokecha me'imach*, God will seek it out from
you, פרט ליורש *Prat l'yoresh*, you, not the heir. If it's an
heir who did not make the vow and did not have a
direct obligation to bring it, then the heir is exempt from בל
תאחר bal se'acher. *bal t'acher*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says והאי
מעמך מבעי ליה *ve-hai me'imach mibai leih*, don't you need it to
tell you לקט שכחה פאה *Leket Shichcha Peah*? Which was as we
pointed out multiple times the most bizarre inclusion in the בל תאחר
*bal t'acher* category. But anyway he learned it out from there because
those are פסוקים pesukim, *psukim* where the תורה Torah *Torah* says the
poor person עני עמך *ani imach*, with you. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says קרי ביה מעמך וקרי ביה עמך *kari be me'imach v'kari
be imach*. No, it has, since it says מעמך *me'imach*, the עמך
*imach* tells you לקט שכחה פאה *Leket Shichcha Peah* and the מ׳
*mem* of מעמך *me'imach* tells you only you not your heir. It's
funny the phrase קרי ביה *kari be* because normally the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* just says no there's an extra מ׳ *mem*, קרי ביה *kari
be* often suggests a different way to read the verse. But anyway
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying you learn both out. So interestingly
although as we said בל תאחר *bal t'acher* does not require you
to make the vow, like if you're obligated in a חטאת *chatas*
or an אשם *asham*, it does have to start with you. So
even though you're obligated to bring this קרבן korban, *korban* because you
inherited it and there might still be the מצוות עשה *mitzvas asei*
of ובאת שמה והבאת שמה *u'vashta shama v'heveisa shama*, there is not
בל תאחר *bal t'acher*. Okay, בעי רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira *Bay Rabbi
Zeira*, now רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira* had another question. אישה מה היא
בבל Bavel. תאחר *isha mah hee b'bal t'acher*? Is a woman transgress
בל תאחר *bal t'acher*? Now that's bizarre, why not? She took a
vow, she's obligated, why shouldn't she? So מי אמרינן הא לא מחייבא
בראיה *mi amrinan ha lo mechayva b'reiah*? Now this is quite fascinating
because again since the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*, the תורה Torah *Torah* doesn't
connect it to the רגלים regalim *regalim* at all. All we've been
learning in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is a connection to the רגלים
regalim *regalim*, and so maybe a woman doesn't have to be עולה
לרגל oleh laregel *oleh l'regel*. A woman could stay at home while
her husband is עולה לרגל *oleh l'regel*. So therefore the significance of
having had that opportunity to bring it during the רגל regel *regel*
and the רגל *regel* being a significant time you had a chance,
you didn't bring it, it's בל תאחר *bal t'acher*, that doesn't apply
to a woman. So maybe since she could stay at home the
whole time and never be in ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim*, so she never
squandered an opportunity. So maybe there's never sense of... איחור, ichur right?
Now obviously the גמרא Gemara before spoke a whole idea of a
year, so according to the idea before that there's just an איחור
ichur because of time on the calendar, you're a year late, then
that would. But if you emphasize איחור ichur delay in the context
of רגלים regalim, and squandered opportunities, so maybe it would not apply
to a woman. So therefore maybe she does not have בל תאחר,
או דילמא o dilma perhaps we say האישה בשמחה. haisha besimcha. She's
included in the מצוה mitzvah of שמחה, simcha, ושמחת אתה וביתך, vesamachta
ata uveitecha,
and therefore she has to be in ירושלים Yerushalayim in order to
experience שמחה, simcha, and therefore she is in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, so
what do we say?
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now אמר ליה אביי amar
lei Abaye by
the way, even though היא חייבת בשמחה hi chayaves besimcha doesn't mean
she actually goes into the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash. but nevertheless being
עולה לרגל to be have the שמחה simcha together in ירושלים Yerushalayim.
might be enough. אמר ליה אביי amar lei Abaye so אביי Abaye
said back to רבי זירא, ותיפוק ליה דהא אישה בשמחה. veseipak lei
deha isha besimcha. So he says
yeah, okay, that's a good enough reason. She's part of שמחה. simcha.
What's your question? She has to be in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Now again,
even with that you could have said she doesn't have to be
in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Anyway, but let's take a look.
But for אביי Abaye that was enough. So the גמרא Gemara. says
ומי אמר אביי הכי? umi amar Abaye hachi? Did אביי Abaye really
say that that's obviously enough? והאמר אביי אישה בעלה משמחה. veha'amar Abaye
isha ba'alah mesamchah. A husband a woman her husband you know gives
her joy, which means now which means what does that mean? So
רש"י Rashi says it means that she doesn't have to eat קרבנות.
korbanos. That the idea of שמחה simcha which is which is שלמי
שמחה shalmei simcha is not applied to a woman. It's another form
of שמחה, simcha, nice clothing and so on. And therefore she doesn't
have to be anywhere even near ירושלים. Yerushalayim The husband it could
be like you know what they do now when they go to
where do they אומן, Uman, you know where there's all these interesting
stories like you know oh these husbands are abandoning their wives like
some of their wives not not all of them I can't speak
for the women but some of their wives say love it, get
rid of the husband we'll have this time to ourselves, you know
all the women get together. So you know he he leaves her
gives her some nice clothes, maybe everybody's happy. Okay, separate vacation. So
that's what רש"י Rashi says. She doesn't have to be in ירושלים.
Yerushalayim, תוספות Tosafos says no, she would have to be in ירושלים
Yerushalayim to eat the שלמי שמחה, shalmei simcha, but the point is
she wouldn't have to bring the שלמי שמחה, shalmei simcha, right?
Let me see this תוספות. Tosafos. Yeah,
three lines from the bottom ומפרש רבנו תם בעלה משמחה שהחיוב אבעלה
ולא עלה ולפיכך לא קרינא ביה ובאת שמה, umefaresh Rabbeinu Tam ba'alah
mesamchah shehachiyuv aba'alah velo aleha ulfichach lo karina bei uvas shama, right?
So yes, the husband maybe she partakes in the שלמי שמחה, shalmei
simcha, but she's not the one that has to come to the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash The husband brings the קרבנות korbanos, and has
her eat from the קרבנות. korbanos. Okay, so therefore so therefore there
is that might be enough to say that she's not it's not
an idea of בל תאחר. Okay,
so let's take a look.
What about the unmarried girls? I mean that's a good point.
So they're not then certainly they're not obligated. It's fundamentally an obligation
on the men. But even when they're even when they're included in
שמחה simcha because אתה וביתך, ata uveitecha, they're still not the ones
going to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash, Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says if they're not the ones going to the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash or according to רש"י Rashi it's not even related to the
קרבנות, korbanos why is this relevant? לדברי רבי זירא קאמרת. lidvrei Rabbi
Zeira kaamart. No, according to רבי זירא I hold they're not even
going into the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, they're not even eating קרבנות.
korbanos, But you רבי זירא that you mentioned the idea of אישה
בשמחה, isha besimcha, presumably you hold they are eating from the בשר
קרבנות basar korbanos or maybe you even
hold that they would bring שלמי שמחה shalmei simcha although that we've
never heard. Anyway, shouldn't that be enough? So again, this is quite
fascinating because it gets to the issue, you know, is בל תאחר
just איחור like we just say it's like past a year, which
is what we had before, calendar time? Or there's a specific link
to the רגלים regalim, and if it's linked to the רגלים, regalim.
then maybe it's not enough that it's a רגל. Maybe it's a
רגל in which you have an obligation to be in the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash. or maybe obligation to be in ירושלים, that might
be the difference here with the case of the woman, to be
in ירושלים to eat the קרבן korban but not to be in
the בית המקדש, and that defines the sense of a squandered opportunity
and that defines בל תאחר. Yes, Michael?
One thing that I wanted to ask before was one of the
things they said was on בל תאחר was צדקות. tzedakos. I mean
does that mean like let's say I make an and I get
an עליה aliyah and you know and I say בעבור שנדרתי ba'avur
shenadarti $180 בית הכנסת? Beis Haknesses?
Well, first of all we already talked. That בית הכנסת Beis Haknesses
might be it might not be the צדקה. Under what category does
בית הכנסת Beis Haknesses fall? So does it fall under any category?
Does it fall under a type of a you know סתם נדר
stam neder or a type of a בדק הבית? bedek habayis? So
it's not exactly clear where it falls under, but צדקות tzedakos the
גמרא Gemara particularly emphasizes עניים and gives it a different timeframe because
of קיימי עניים. kaimi aniyim. So and
but yes, you know, I mean that's why people are often very
מקפיד makpid to say בלי נדר bli neder and so on. Not
just so that if they don't do it they don't violate their
נדר, but also so they will not be בל תאחר. But yes,
it is a very fascinating discussion about, you know, real issues about
at what stage is there real בל תאחר by when you pledge
to give money and it's over a certain time. Okay, but I'm
not going to give you a full הלכה halakha answer. Okay, so
איבעיא להו. ibaya lehu. That would be a separate שיעור, shiur,
which I won't give. איבעיא להו. ibaya lehu. They asked... Question: בכור
מאימתי מונין לו שנה? bechor me-eimatai monim lo shana?
Now this is not בל תאחר because this is once we're talking
about a time frame. The תורה Torah, says that you're supposed to
eat a בכור שנה בשנה, bechor shana be-shana, every year. So when
does you start counting the year for a בכור? bechor?
אביי אמר משעה שנולד, Abaye amar me-sha'ah she-nolad, from the day
it's born.
רב אחא בר יעקב אמר משעה שראוי להרצאה, Rav Acha bar Yaakov
amar me-sha'ah she-ra'uy le-hartza'ah,
the time it's fit to be brought as a קרבן, korban from
eight days old. ולא פליגי, ve-la pligi, says the גמרא, Gemara it's
not a debate. הא בתם הא בבעל מום. ha be-tam ha be-ba'al
mum. If it's if it's born without a blemish, then it's fit
to be a קרבן, korban then you don't start until day eight.
If it's born with a blemish, then it's not going to be
brought as a קרבן korban. and therefore you start immediately. Okay, the
idea because what do you do with a בכור bechor with a
blemish? You don't even redeem it as we said, you can't redeem
it because you didn't instill it with קדושה, kedusha, naturally has קדושה,
kedusha, and the כהן Kohen eats it with a blemish outside of
the בית המקדש.
So therefore the idea of a year there would be would start
from the day it was born. So the גמרא Gemara says...
I'm sorry we just switched there in the middle. So which one
is it?
If it's
if it's a תם tam then you get from when it was
born or from when it's... from after eight days old? because it's
only you only start counting the year from the time it's fit
to be brought, which is after eight days old. So the גמרא
Gemara says הא בתם ha be-tam and בבעל מום be-ba'al mum you
start counting immediately because it's fit because it would be fit to
be שחט shachted and eaten immediately, so the year would start immediately
from the day it's born. So the גמרא Gemara. says בעל מום
מאימת יאכיל ליה? ba'al mum me-eimat yachil lei? Since when can you
eat a בעל מום ba'al mum the day it's born? Because you
know רש"י Rashi is sort of saying if it's born you know
maybe it's a נפל, nefel, maybe it's a maybe it's like a
you know and not going to survive and therefore it can't be
eaten, especially if it has a מום. mum. So דקים ליה בדאיכא
דכלו לו חדשיו. de-kim lei be-de-ika de-kalu lo chodashav. No, sometimes an
animal can be born and it's clear that it has a full
nine months of gestation and it's clear that it's fully born of
health and it's not a concern of it being a נפל, nefel,
and there are cases where you can eat an animal the day
it's born, and therefore you would start counting the year from the
day it's born. What problem do you have there, Charlie?
I mean that's saying that a decree from the תורה Torah is
conditional.
What do you mean what are you talking about?
I mean I just find that surprising.
What decree is conditional? What are you talking about?
So if you think you can figure out that it was full
you the truth is you rarely know ever how long the gestation
was, okay.
But what decree is conditional? This is just a הלכה halakha of
whether you're concerned that it might be a נפל nefel or not.
How do you how can you be sure?
Whatever, הלכה halakha. has different ways of defining, I don't understand what's
bothering you. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our Rabbis taught. I'm serious, we
make assessments all the time in הלכה. halacha Because it says שנה
בשנה. shana be-shana.
What are you doing?
What are you waiting? You're either eating for I don't know, you
you don't want to שחט shacht it the first day, you know
you're procrastinating... to שחט shacht it? No, I'm sorry if I wasn't
clear, you have to eat it or not you have to I
mean בדיעבד be-di'avad you can do it afterwards, but you're supposed to
eat a בכור bechor within the year. Okay, I'm sorry if that
wasn't clear, שנה בשנה shana be-shana לפני ה' אלהיך תאכלנו שנה בשנה.
lifnei Hashem Elokecha tachalenu shana be-shana.
So you're supposed to eat the בכור bechor within its first year.
So the question is how is that first year defined?
You're supposed to eat it within the first year?
Yeah, either eat it or bring it as a קרבן within the
first year. Now are you over on בל תאחר if you have
the year without having the שלוש רגלים? regalim I don't know exactly.
Okay, but this is at least the idea of שנה בשנה. shana
be-shana. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our Rabbis taught: באחד בניסן ראש השנה
לחדשים. be-echad be-Nissan Rosh HaShanah le-chodashim.
So now we're done sort of with some of the בל תאחר,
okay, and now we're going to look at the rest of the
day at a different ברייתות braisos that that have other things that
are on the list of ראשי שנה rashei shana that we did
not have in our משנה. Mishnah. Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, באחד
בניסן be-echad be-Nissan on the first of ניסן, Nissan, ראש השנה לחדשים,
Rosh HaShanah le-chodashim,
it's ראש השנה Rosh HaShanah for the months, meaning you ניסן Nissan
starts it's month one החודש הראשון ha-chodesh ha-rishon בחודש השני ba-chodesh ha-sheni
etc. I mean that's most explicit in the תורה, Torah right? לעיבורין,
le-iburim, for making a a a leap year, we'll see what that
means, sounds like you decide on ראש השנה Rosh HaShanah on ניסן
Nissan whether to make a leap year which is already 12 months
in advance. ולתרומת שקלים, u-le-trumas shekalim, which is clear we learned we
learned שקלים, Shekalim, means that the bringing the קרבנות korbanos, from the
new שקל shekel starts at the starts on ראש חודש ניסן. Rosh
Chodesh Nissan. We know that's why in the beginning of אדר Adar
you go and you send the שלוחים shluchim out and you start
collecting the שקלים shekalim because you bring
the new
the קרבנות ציבור korbanos tzibur are that they come from communal funds
and you recollect it every year and you start bringing from the
new funds on ניסן. Nissan. ויש אומרים אף לשכירות בתים, ve-yesh omrim
af li-schirus batim, and some say even for renting houses, that if
you say to somebody I'm renting you this house or this apartment
if you say for a year then it's 12 months, but if
you say until the end of the year, so the end of
the year means when? And they're saying well when comes until the
last day in אדר Adar and the first day of ניסן Nissan
is already a new year. So that's quite fascinating. I mean again
supposedly if you're using the years of kings for your שטרות shtaros
and your secular financial documents and those get incremented on ראש חודש
ניסן, Rosh Chodesh Nissan, then it's not crazy to say that when
you do other financial transactions and you refer to the year that
you refer to a year which which starts again and gets incremented
on ראש חודש ניסן. Rosh Chodesh Nissan. Is that clear? logical connection
of those two? Again if in your locale they use the secular
dates and the secular kings and they do it by
ראש חודש ניסן.
Rosh Chodesh Nissan. Isn't the rent adjusted the same way that when
you purchase a land it depends on how many years?
Yeah, so that's an interesting question. If somebody basically says, if the
document says like 'til the end of the year and the money
is like clearly six months of rent based on whatever the going
rate is, but you know, ראש חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh Nissan is
a month away, what do you do? Do you say, well, clearly
it meant ראש חודש תשרי, Rosh Chodesh Tishrei, it didn't mean ראש
חודש ניסן, Rosh Chodesh Nissan, you know, or do you say, no,
you know, maybe it was a maybe he just paid a lot
for the apartment, you know? So that becomes an interesting question. I'll
get we'll discuss it in a little bit when we get into
the גמרא. Gemara. So let's take a look. So, okay, לחדשים מנא
לן? lichdashim minah lan? How do you know? So we're a little
behind now, but you're going to see this דף is going to
go super fast. How do you know that ניסן Nissan is the
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh for it starts the counting of the months,
that it's the first month is ניסן Nissan and the second is
אייר Iyar and so on? דכתיב, de'chesiv, the פסוק pasuk says, החודש
הזה לכם ראש חדשים ראשון הוא לכם לחדשי השנה, hachodesh hazeh lachem
rosh chodashim rishon hu lachem lechodshei hashanah, דברו אל כל עדת בני
ישראל לאמר בעשור לחודש הזה ויקחו להם איש שה לבית אבות שה
לבית. dabru el kol adat bnei yisrael lemor be'asor lachodesh hazeh veyikchu
lahem ish seh leveit avot seh labayit. So that's where the תורה
Torah says that the first month, this month that פסח Pesach comes
is the first month and that's how it gets started counting as
one and that's why the other months in the תורה Torah. is
חודש השני chodesh hasheini and חודש השלישי, chodesh hashelishi, etc., and it's
the month that פסח Pesach was brought. Now, I don't know, so
because it helps fill up the דף, והיה לכם למשמרת עד ארבעה
עשר יום לחודש הזה ושחטו אתו, vehaya lachem lemishmeret ad arba'ah asar
yom lachodesh hazeh veshachatu oto, basically to prove the reason it quoted
the whole פסוק, pasuk: it could have said וגומר, vegomer, but was
to get to the last point that the month which is ראש
חדשים rosh chodashim is the month that the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
was brought. Okay, so and that's going to be important because how
do we know which month פסח Pesach was brought, right? I mean,
it's a little circular. Oh, it was obviously brought in ניסן Nissan
because it says ראש... it says the first month. How do you
know which... which month was that? How do we know which month
פסח Pesach was brought? We know that the month that it was
brought was called month number one. So here's how we know which
month it was brought. דכתיב, de'chesiv, another פסוק pasuk? says, שמור את
חודש האביב ועשית פסח לה' אלהיך. shamor et chodesh ha'aviv ve'asita pesach
la'Hashem elokecha. So we know that the פסח Pesach is brought in
the month of the אביב, aviv, spring. And אביב aviv is understood
to be the month in which the wheat ripens, okay, or the
barley is the ripening of the grain. And that clearly is ניסן.
Nissan. איזהו חודש שיש בו אביב? eizehu chodesh sheyesh bo aviv? What
is the month that has this ripening of the grain? הוי אומר
זה ניסן. hevei omer zeh Nissan. It's ניסן Nissan וקרי ליה ראשון.
vekari lei rishon. So we see אביב aviv was the קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach where... and that we know is ניסן, Nissan, and therefore
we know that ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, that the first month is
ניסן. Nissan. גמרא Gemara says, ואימא אייר? ve'eima Iyar? What about אייר?
Iyar? How about אייר? Iyar? Maybe, you know, there's still some ripening
going on. No, בעינן אביב וליכא, be'inan aviv ve'leka, there's no real
ripening of the grain still happening in אייר. Iyar. ואימא אדר? ve'eima
Adar? What about אדר? Adar? Some grain ripens early. No, בעינן רוב
אביב וליכא. be'inan rov aviv ve'leka. You need it to be the
primary month of the ripening. So גמרא Gemara asks, מידי רוב אביב
כתיב? midi rov aviv kesiv? It doesn't say the primary month of
the ripening. Maybe אדר Adar is already considered to be אביב. aviv.
Maybe פסח Pesach happened in אדר. Adar. אלא אמר רב חסדא מהכא,
ella amar Rav Chisda mehacha, fine, this פסוק: pasuk אך בחמשה עשר
יום לחודש השביעי באספכם את תבואת הארץ. ach bachamishah asar yom lachodesh
hashevi'i be'aspechem et tvuat ha'aretz. So we'll try to do another thing
which we can infer it based on the agricultural period. In the
seventh month on the fifteenth day, סוכות, Sukkot, באספכם את תבואת הארץ,
be'aspechem et tvuat ha'aretz,
when you gather in the grain, you know, it's been drying out
in the field. איזהו חודש שיש בו אסיפה? eizehu chodesh sheyesh bo
asifah? What's the month that you gather in the grain? הוי אומר
זה תשרי וקרי ליה שביעי. hevei omer zeh Tishrei vekari lei shevi'i.
It's תשרי Tishrei וקרי ליה שביעי, vekari lei shevi'i, and it's called
the seventh month. So therefore you see that clearly ניסן Nissan is
the first. ואימא מרחשון? ve'eima Marheshvan? Nah, how do you know,
maybe it's מרחשון? Marheshvan? מאי שביעי שביעי לאייר? mai shevi'i shevi'i le'Iyar?
Maybe אייר Iyar is number one and therefore, you know, סוכות Sukkot
falls out on מרחשון. Marheshvan. No, בעינן אסיף וליכא, be'inan asif ve'leka,
there's no real gathering of the grain still happening in מרחשון. Marheshvan.
ואימא אלול? ve'eima Elul? How about אלול? Elul? מאי שביעי שביעי לאדר?
mai shevi'i shevi'i le'Adar? That
since we already said that some of the grain begins to ripen
in אדר, Adar, that could mean that some of them of the
gathering in begins to happen in, right, in what do you call
it, in אייר... Iyar. no, in אלול. Elul Okay,
so maybe אלול Elul is the beginning of the gathering in the
same way אדר Adar was the beginning of the ripening. No, בעינן
רוב אסיף וליכא, be'inan rov asif ve'leka, you need the month that
is predominantly about gathering in. So גמרא Gemara, asks the same question,
מידי רוב אסיף כתיב? midi rov asif kesiv? It doesn't say predominantly
about gathering in. So just because they're linked to agricultural periods does
not exactly fix it on ניסן Nissan or on תשרי. Tishrei. There
could still be maybe the early stuff could be a month earlier.
אלא אמר רבינא, ella amar Ravina, fine. דבר זה מתורת משה רבינו
לא למדנו. devar zeh mitorat Moshe Rabbeinu lo lamadnu. We did not,
we cannot really prove it from the תורה because obviously there needs
to be a fixed point of reference which is not exactly you're
able to find in the תורה. מדברי קבלה למדנו, midivrei kabbalah lamadnu,
but we can learn it from the words of קבלה kabbalah meaning
from the נביאים Nevi'im and the כתובים. Ketuvim. And now what we're
going to do is we're going to quote פסוקים, pesukim if you
take a look down the side, basically from זכריה Zechariah and אסתר
Esther which both share the quality of being post the first חורבן
הבית Churban Habayit and coming back from the exile and therefore importing
the names of the Babylonian months and these these פסוקים pesukim... are
going to identify the numbered month with the named month because this
is when the names month begins is when they have had this.
experience of בבל Bavel, and they have adopted the use of those
names. So let's take a look. ביום עשרים וארבעה לעשתי עשר חודש
הוא חודש שבט Beyom esrim vearbaah leashtei asar chodesh hu chodesh Shevat
on the twenty-fourth day of the eleventh month, which is שבט, Shevat,
of שבט Shevat is eleven and ניסן Nisan is one. רבא בר
עולא אמר מהכא: Rava bar Ulla amar me-hacha: ותילקח אסתר אל המלך
אחשוורוש אל בית מלכותו בחודש העשירי הוא חודש טבת. Vatilakach Ester el
ha-melech Achashveirosh el beit malchuto ba-chodesh ha-asiri hu chodesh Tevet.
So the tenth is טבת, Tevet, so one is ניסן. Nisan. רב
כהנא אמר מהכא: Rav Kahana amar me-hacha: וארבעה עשר לחודש התשיעי בכסלו.
Ve-arbaah asar le-chodesh ha-tshii be-Chislev. Fine. רב אחא בר יעקב אמר מהכא:
Rav Acha bar Yaakov amar me-hacha: ויקראו סופרי המלך בעת ההיא בחודש
השלישי הוא חודש סיון. Vayikareu sofrei ha-melech ba-et ha-hi ba-chodesh ha-shlishi hu
chodesh Sivan. Alright,
so three is סיון. Sivan. רב אשי אמר מהכא: Rav Ashi amar
me-hacha: הפיל פור הוא הגורל לפני המן מיום ליום ומחודש לחודש שנים
עשר הוא חודש אדר. Hipil pur hu ha-goral lifnei Haman mi-yom le-yom
u-me-chodesh le-chodesh shneim asar hu chodesh Adar. So אדר Adar is twelve,
so ניסן Nisan is one. ואיבעית אימא מהכא: Ve-iba'it eima me-hacha: בחודש
הראשון הוא חודש ניסן. Ba-chodesh ha-rishon hu chodesh Nisan.
So that was nice. So the גמרא Gemara says,
if so, וכולהו
מאי טעמא לא אמרי מהאי? Ve-kuleihu mai taama la amri me-hai? Why
did everybody else not quote this פסוק? pasuk No, דדילמא ראשון ראשון
למילתא. De-dilma rishon rishon le-milta.
So now, maybe it says בחודש ראשון Ba-chodesh rishon means the first
month that this whole story began to happen. So that wasn't explicit
that it means the first month in the numbering of the months.
So we wanted the other פסוקים... yeah, that already... then we wouldn't
have said. I don't know. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says, ותנא דידן,
Ve-tanna didan, now why did our תנא tanna not say that ניסן
Nisan was the beginning of the numbering of the months? So it
says בשנים קמיירי בחודשים לא קמיירי. Be-shanim ka-mairi be-chodashim lo ka-mairi. It's
not dealing with months. It's dealing with the entire year. So this
issue of months numbering is not its interest. You could also say,
by the way, that months numbering was no longer relevant once you
started using named months, right? It stopped being, I mean, it's, you
know, a relevant thing להלכה, le-halacha, this issue of the numbers. By
the way, תוספות Tosafot makes two points very quickly. תוספות Tosafot מדברי
קבלה לא למדנו. Mi-divrei kabbalah lo lamadnu. תוספות Tosafot says, ומסיק למילף
מכאן מנא לן כלל אם לא נאמר שיש קבלה בידם סדר שמות
החדשים זה אחר זה. U-masik le-meilaf mi-kan mna lan klal im lo
nomar she-yesh kabbalah be-yadam seder shemot ha-chodashim zeh achar zeh.
תוספות Tosafot says, look, there's not really a fixed point here either.
Just because you're saying month one is ניסן, Nisan, it begs the
question which is, and when is ניסן? Nisan? Okay, right?
So what? So who says, you know, who says ניסן Nisan is
what we identify? So obviously, you have to have some fixed point.
So if we already know what the order of the months are,
right, and which, you know, which is first and which comes next
and so on, then you're able to, once you link in the
numbers, to know what we're talking about. Okay, and by the way,
and I just want to read the next line. והכי אמר בירושלמי
שמות החדשים עלו בידם מבבל. Ve-hachi amar bi-Yerushalmi shemot ha-chodashim alu be-yadam
mi-Bavel.
So the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says very clearly, they adopted the names of
the months from בבל. Bavel. בראשונה, Ba-rishonah, originally, in the נביאים, neviim,
like if you look in מלכים Melachim and so on, it says
בירח האיתנים. Be-yerach ha-eitanim. It calls the month the month of איתנים.
Eitanim. What does that mean? שבו נולדו אבות, She-bo noldu avot, the
strong ones. That's when the forefathers were born. We'll see this later
in the גמרא. Gemara בירח בול, Be-yerach Bul, or another month is
called the month of בול. Bul. This is in תנ"ך, Tanakh, earlier.
שבו כל העולם נובל. She-bo kol ha-olam novel.
That's when there's like the, you know, the fall, the leaves are
falling down. וארץ עשויה בולות בולות שבו בוללים לבהמה בבתיהם. Ve-eretz asuyah
bulot bulot she-bo bolelim la-behemah be-vateihem. בירח זיו, Be-yerach Ziv, שבו זיווה
של אילנות, She-bo zivah shel ilanot, that
that's when the trees are blossoming. So what he says is there
actually was an interesting transition. In the early period of the time
they were in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, the months were also associated
with maybe more descriptive names that described agricultural events, you know, and
maybe those were beginning to become names of months. But then, at
the next stage, there were like three stages: first numbers, then descriptive
names of agricultural things, and then the names that were adopted from
בבל. Of course, the names that were adopted from בבל, some of
them relate to Babylonian gods, so which raises very interesting questions. Okay,
back to the גמרא.
Gemara And so there's two points.
וליעבורי... Ve-le'iburei... that, I don't know, that was the two points. One
was that you needed to have, you needed already to know the
order of the months, and the other was that the months were
adopted from בבל.
Did they never ever thought of that question, you know, up until
now? Like how do we know that ניסן Nisan is the first
month, you know? Right, and you always take it
for
a fixed point of reference. Exactly. Am I totally ruining my phone
here? Okay, so now, wow, I really just did a nice job
on myself just now. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. וליבורים... Ve-le-iburim... so the גמרא Gemara says, וליבורים. Ve-le-iburim. וליבורים Ve-le-iburim
says the גמרא, Gemara מניסן
מנינן? Mi-Nisan maninan? We count from ניסן? Nisan? I'm sorry, I misread
that. וליבורים מניסן מנינן? Ve-le-iburim mi-Nisan maninan? Do we really count עיבורים
iburim from ניסן? Nisan? והתניא, Ve-ha-tanya, and it's taught in the ברייתא:
braita: אין מעברין השנה לפני ראש השנה, Ein me'avrin ha-shanah lifnei Rosh
Hashanah, ואם עיברוה אינה מעוברת, Ve-im ibruha einah me'uberet, that you do
not...
because the גמרא Gemara. assumes it means that you assess whether to
make a leap year on ניסן, Nisan, which is really a whole
twelve months in advance. But the ברייתא braita says you don't do
it too early. You don't do it before ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah,
before תשרי. Tishrei. And if you did it, it doesn't even work.
אבל מפני הדחק, Aval mipnei ha-dochak,
if there's a concern of pressure, which basically means like רש"י Rashi
says, you're afraid for example that there might be an edict from
the Roman government that won't let you do עיבור שנה ibur shanah
later on, or you might not have the נשיא nasi might not
be available and you need the נשיא nasi to be involved, then
מעברין אותה אחר ראש השנה מיד, Me'avrin otah achar Rosh Hashanah mi-yad,
you can do it immediately after ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. ואף על
פי כן אין מעברין אלא אדר, Ve-af al pi chen ein me'avrin
ela Adar, and anyway, whenever you do it, the only month that
you can add is an extra month of אדר. Adar. Okay, that's
because it says, you know, that's because we learn it out from
אביב, Aviv, and therefore since the point of the עיבור ibur is
to make sure פסח Pesach. falls out in the spring, then the
adjustment occurs right before פסח. Pesach Pesach and occurs in אדר. Adar.
Anyway you see here that it can only be done from תשרי
Tishrei and we say that it can be done all the way
from ניסן. Nisan. Okay once we, one of the reasons that you
don't want to do it too early in advance is that the
word people will forget, right? You want to sort of have it
that it's within the context that people remember, okay, we're making an
עיבור ibbur year and they know that it's what's going to happen.
You don't want to do it too much in advance. Also the
reasons for doing it might change if you do it too much
in advance. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר
רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman Bar Yitzchak, מאי עיבורין? mai
ibburin? הפסקת עיבורין. hafsakat ibburin. Now, when it means it's the ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah for עיבורין, ibburin, it means that when ניסן Nisan
comes about, you can no longer make it a leap year. Since
you can only make a leap year in אדר, Adar, the last
opportunity to make an עיבור ibbur year, a leap year, is the
last day of אדר. Adar. Then you could say now we're going
to have an אדר שני. Adar Sheni. But once it's the first
day of ניסן, Nisan, it's too late to make a
leap year. דתנן, Detnan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, הן העידו,
hen he'idu, they, which is the same people we had before which
was רב פפייס Rav Papias ורבי יהושע, v'Rabbi Yehoshua, they testified, this
is again going to עדיות, Eduyot, שמעברין השנה כל אדר, she'me'abrin hashanah
kol Adar, that you can do the, you can do a leap
year the entire אדר. Adar. You can wait till the very last
day of אדר Adar before adding a second אדר. Adar. שהיו אומרים,
Shehayu omrim, they used to say עד הפורים, ad ha'Purim, you cannot
do it after פורים, Purim, right? You can't do it at the
very, very last minute. And now we see you can do it
all of אדר. Adar. מאי טעמא דמאן דאמר עד הפורים? Mai ta'ama
deman de'amar ad ha'Purim? What was that logic? כיון דאמר מר, Keivan
de'amar mar, because since we teach שואלין בהלכות הפסח קודם לפסח שלשים
יום, sholin b'hilchot haPesach kodem l'Pesach shloshim yom, that you start talking
about פסח Pesach 30 days before, so what's going to happen after
פורים? Purim? You're going to start teaching הלכות פסח. hilchot Pesach. And
that meaning, you're sending a message to everybody that it's going to
be פסח Pesach in 30 days. And then you decide to make
an עיבור ibbur year and then it's not going to be פסח
Pesach for another 60 days. Okay, so אתו לזלזולי בחמץ, atu l'zulzulei
b'chametz,
they'll come to be, to treat lightly the prohibition of חמץ. chametz.
Now, where would, when will they treat it lightly? I assumed what
it meant was that this year they'll get the message that it's
a leap year, but then they'll also have internalized a different message.
They'll have internalized the message that even when we start learning about
הלכות הפסח, hilchot haPesach, it might not necessarily wind up to be
פסח Pesach 30 days from now, and maybe next year, you know,
they won't treat the actual פסח Pesach. as the real פסח. Pesach
It's like the time I have when you do too many fire
drills but then you say don't, don't, you don't have to get
up, it's just a drill. So then you teach everybody to ignore
it. So, okay, you're teaching me to ignore the learning because this
year we did the learning and it was another 60 and it
wasn't פסח Pesach right away. רש"י Rashi says no, רש"י Rashi says
the problem is this year you'll לזלזולי, l'zulzulei, you won't believe it
when you heard it's a leap year. Nah, it's not a leap
year, we've been learning הלכות פסח hilchot Pesach over the last two
weeks, and therefore you'll make פסח Pesach. in אדר שני Adar Sheni
and when it really comes ניסן, Nisan, you won't believe that it's
פסח. Pesach Okay, anyway you don't want to confuse people at the
last minute so you what, you can only do it before פורים.
Purim. ואידך, V'idach, the other one said no, מעבדי ידעו דשתא מעברתא
בחושבנא תליא מילתא, me'evadei yedu d'shata me'ubarta b'chushbana talya milta,
people know that an עיבור ibbur year is, depends on calculations and
it's always, you know, it's always like being figured out and adjusted
and determined. וסברי חושבנא הוא דלא סליק להו לרבנן עד השתא, V'savri
chushbana hu d'lo salik lehu l'rabbanan ad hashta, and
people understand, yeah, the rabbis didn't exactly, you know, figure out the
calculations and exactly make the determination until now and they'll accept the
reality that yes, you do have an עיבור ibbur year and they'll
and it won't, you know, lead to them dismissing it. Okay, ותנא
דידן, V'tana didan, now, so now we know why we said that
it's ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah for עיבורין, ibburin, which means that this
becomes, ends your opportunity for making an עיבור ibbur year. It starts
a new year and the previous year, if the previous year is
going to be a leap year, it has to occur before ניסן.
Nisan. Okay, ותנא דידן, V'tana didan, and our תנא, tanna, בהתחלה קא
מיירי בהפסקה לא קא מיירי. b'hatchala ka mairi b'hafsaka lo ka mairi.
He's interested in ways in which the year starts at ניסן, Nisan,
not the way in which the previous year ends. Because again, the
עיבור ibbur year doesn't start in ניסן Nisan because you can't determine,
make it a leap year from ניסן, Nisan, you have to wait
till תשרי. Tishrei. ניסן Nisan only ends the previous year as its
potential to being a leap year. Okay, so that's the idea of
an עיבור ibbur year, yes?
Somewhere I don't remember where it was, there's a passage that indicates
חזקיהו Chizkiyahu retroactively declared ניסן Nisan to be אדר. Adar.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So there's a גמרא Gemara about that, that one
of the things he did שחטאו ולא הודו לו חכמים she'chato v'lo
hodu lo chachamim etc. Yeah, right. Okay. All right, so ותרומת שקלים,
u'trumat shekalim, you know,
collecting new funds and the collection happens earlier but drawing on the
new funds for bringing the קרבנות ציבור, korbanot tzibur, the communal sacrifices.
מנלן? Menalan? Where is
this from? אמר רבי יאשיה אמר קרא, Amar Rabbi Yoshiah amar kra,
says Rabbi Yoshiah says the verse, זאת עולת חודש בחדשו לחדשי השנה.
Zot olat chodesh b'chodsho l'chodshei hashanah. This is the עולה of the
month in its right month for the months of the year. So
אמר תורה חדש והבא קרבן מתרומה חדשה. Amar Torah chadesh v'havei korban
mitruma chadasha.
Part of what it's saying is בחדשי השנה b'chodshei hashanah you should
renew it, and these communal sacrifices have to come from new funds
each year. Meaning it's taken for granted that communal sacrifices come from
communal funds, that's what makes them communal. But בחדשי השנה b'chodshei hashanah
says it has to be renewed each year. Okay. וגמרי שנה שנה
מניסן. V'gamrei shana shana mi'Nisan. And how do you know it's ניסן?
Nisan? 'Cause here it says לחדשי השנה, l'chodshei hashanah, and by ניסן
Nisan it says דכתיב ראשון הוא לכם לחדשי השנה, dechtiv rishon hu
lachem l'chodshei hashanah, like we quoted before.
So the same way that's ניסן, Nisan, this idea of renewing is
at ניסן. Nisan. And
we know, we'll discuss later that that's ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, that's
תשרי. Tishrei. So no, the גמרא says no, דנים שנה שיש עמה
חודשים משנה שיש עמה חודשים. danim shanah she-yeish imah chadashim mishanah she-yeish
imah chadashim. Now,
by the idea of the new קרבנות, it said חודשי השנה, chodshei
hashanah, it has months of the year. And by ניסן Nissan it
says ראשון הוא לכם לחודשי השנה, rishon hu lachem l'chodshei hashanah, months
of the year. So those are very linked phrases. They both have
year and months. ואין דנים שנה שיש עמה חודשים משנה שאין עמה
חודשים. v'ein danim shanah she-yeish imah chadashim mishanah she-ein imah chadashim. You
don't apply a verse where it says year with months, you know,
that this is a new קרבן בלחודשי השנה, l'chodshei hashanah, from a
verse that has the word year without months, by ראש השנה, Rosh
Hashanah, מראשית השנה. meiraishis hashanah. So basically the פסוק posuk, of ניסן,
Nissan, חודשי השנה, chodshei hashanah, and the פסוק of new קרבנות, חודשי
השנה, chodshei hashanah, link and tell you that it begins anew at
ניסן. Nissan. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel,
says Rav in
the name of Shmuel, קרבנות ציבור הבאים באחד בניסן מצוה להביא מן
החדש. korbanot tzibbur habaim b'echad b'Nissan mitzvah l'havi min hachadash. The new
communal sacrifices that come on the first of ניסן, Nissan, right, which
we've been talking about, you have a מצוה mitzvah to bring it
from the new funds. ואם הביא מן הישן יצא, v'im haivi min
hayashan yatza, but still, if you bring it from old funds, it's
still a communal sacrifice and therefore it's still a good קרבן. אלא
שחיסר מצוה, ella she-chisar mitzvah, you lost the מצוה, mitzvah, the idea
of a new year, new funds. תניא נמי הכי, tanya nami hachi,
we taught similarly, קרבנות ציבור הבאים באחד בניסן מצוה להביא מן החדש.
korbanot tzibbur habaim b'echad b'Nissan mitzvah l'havi min hachadash.
There's a מצוה mitzvah to bring them starting on ראש חודש ניסן
Rosh Chodesh Nissan from the new funds. ואם הביא מן הישן יצא
אלא שחיסר מצוה. v'im haivi min hayashan yatza ella she-chisar mitzvah. You
still have your obligation but you lost a מצוה. mitzvah. ויחיד, v'yachid,
now another הלכה since we're talking about it being communal. If an
individual, a private person, שנתנדב משלו, shenitnadav mishelo, contributed, gave his own
animal, here, use this as a communal sacrifice, then כשרים, ksherim, that
you can use that as communal even though it's coming from an
individual. ובלבד שימסרם לציבור, u'vilvad she-yimserem l'tzibbur,
but he has to truly give it over to the community, right?
Instead standard guy'd say, 'Ah, you see that, you see that קרבן
תמיד korban tamid being brought today? That's mine, that's my animal,' right?
So if you're still saying that, then it's not a real קרבן
ציבור. korban tzibbur. So yes, we can take your donations, but you
have to completely sever your relationship with it. It's, you know, don't
longer treat it like yours. No, it's now the ציבור's, tzibbur's, okay?
פשיטא, pshita, obviously
if he's totally giving it over, why's it to be a problem?
No, מהו דתימא ליחוש שמא לא ימסרם לציבור יפה יפה. mahu d'teima
leichosh shema lo yimserem l'tzibbur yafeh yafeh.
Even though it seems like he is, maybe we should be concerned
he's not really, you know, and he'll still wind up talking about
how it was his animal that was brought as a קרבן ציבור.
korban tzibbur. So קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan,
we're not concerned that if it really is, it looks like he
really is and he says he really is, we take him at
his word. ותני דידן, v'tani didan, now why does the author of
our משנה mishnah not mention ניסן Nissan as being the first month
for
what do you call it, for the new שקלים? shkalim? So כיון
דתני אם הביא יצא לא פסיקא ליה. keivan d'tani im hevi yatza
lo psika leih. Since בדיעבד b'diavad you can,
if you're יוצא yotzeh when you bring from the old, it's not
as weighty. You know, it's not absolute. You know, yeah, it's supposed
to be the new funds here, but not in an absolute sense
because בדיעבד b'diavad you could still bring from the old funds. Okay,
ויש אומרים אף לשכירות בתים. v'yeish omrim af l'schirus batim.
The last thing mentioned in this ברייתא braisa is for renting. If
you have a contract and says until the new year or until
the end of the year, it's determined by ניסן, Nissan, which again
works if in general your שטרות shtaros are dated based on ניסן.
Nissan. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, our rabbis taught. המשכיר בית לחברו לשנה,
hamaskir bayis l'chaveiro l'shanah,
if you sell something, if you rent something for a year, for
the duration of a year, then מונה שנים עשר חודש מיום ליום.
moneh shneim asar chodesh miyom l'yom. You go back to the same
date, the same calendar date. So by the way, it's not always
twelve months. If it's a leap year it would be thirteen. The
point is you go back to the same calendar date, you know,
from אדר Adar three until אדר Adar two of the next year.
ואם אמר לשנה זו, v'im amar l'shanah zu,
and if you say 'I'm renting it to you for this year'
until the end of this year, so אפילו לא עמד
אלא באחד באדר כיון שיצא יום אחד בניסן עלתה לו שנה. afilu
lo amad ella b'echad b'Adar keivan she-higia yom echad b'Nissan alsa lo
shanah.
Once the first of ניסן Nissan came about, that's it. That's the
end of the year because the year is defined as ניסן. Nissan.
So you say until the end of the year, yeah, so that
would be, you know, like we would say if it was in
a secular context, if you said 'the end of the year' it
would be understood it stops on December 31st, however many days it
was between now and then. Here too it stops on the last
day of אדר. Adar. Okay, and that's what the point of ניסן
Nissan being ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh means, ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah for
that means. ואפילו למאן דאמר יום אחד בשנה חשוב שנה, v'afilu l'man
d'amar yom echad b'shanah chashuv shanah,
even though in other contexts like when we count the years of
kings and other contexts, we say one day in the year counts
as a year, can already count as a year. So why does
it have to be that you rented it on the first of
אדר? Adar? Maybe you rented it on the 28th of אדר, Adar,
right, and maybe you said 'the end of the year' and you
get it for two days.
Why would we say minimum only if it was a month? גמרא
says no. שאני הכא דלא טרח איניש למיגר ביתא לבציר מתלתין יומין.
shani hacha d'lo tarach inish l'migar beisa l'vatzir mi-tlasin yomin.
People don't rent houses for less than thirty days. They don't go
to the effort of drawing up a contract and renting a house,
right, minimum a month. Like who ever takes out a lease for
less than a month? Okay, so therefore. If it was less than
a month, if it was the twenty-eighth of אדר, Adar, then we
would actually probably say it meant until the end of next year,
right, whereas if it's been said, you know, if it's the first
of אדר Adar we say it's for one month. So the גמרא
says ואימא תשרי. Ve'eima Tishrei. So where do you get ניסן? Nisan?
Right? This is anyway, this is not based on פסוק, this is
just based on convention. So maybe it means תשרי? Tishrei? So גמרא
says no. סתם כי אגר איניש ביתא לכולו ימות גשמים אגר. Stam
ki agar inish beisa l'chulu yemos gshomim agar.
When people rent a house, they want to rent it for the
rainy season, right? This certainly reflects, you know, the reality and the
more susceptibility to the, to the, you know, to the weather. So,
so therefore the rainy season begins when? When do you start saying
ותן טל ומטר לברכה V'sen tal u'matar livracha or משיב הרוח ומוריד
הגשם? Mashiv haruach u'morid hageshem? Right, after תשרי, Tishrei, right? And or
whatever after סוכות. Succos. So therefore,
if you're, if you're renting it, you don't, nobody wants it to
stop right before תשרי. Tishrei. That's the time that you want to
make sure that you've got your house. So it would not make
sense for that to be defined as the year. Okay? Right, for
you understand? Right. Because if you rented it right before תשרי, Tishrei,
it would be crazy that תשרי Tishrei would be when you have
to get evicted. Nobody wants to get evicted right before the rainy
season. Nobody wants to have to start looking for a new house
right before the rainy season. Okay, so that's why it could not
mean the first of תשרי. Tishrei. ותנא קמא דבריתא ותנא דידן בניסן.
V'tanna kamma d'braisa v'tanna didan b'Nisan. So
and how about, this is only a יש אומרים Yeish Omrim for
houses? How about the first opinion did not think ניסן Nisan was
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah for this contract? And the author of our
משנה Mishnah also did not think ניסן Nisan was ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah for renting houses? What's their opinion? So they say בניסן נמי
שכיחי מיטרי. B'Nisan nami shchichi mitri. You know what? In ניסן Nisan
also sometimes you get clouds and sometimes you get rain. So there's
no logical reason to think that you're just as willing to get,
you know, to end your contract, you know, in ניסן. Nisan. Nobody
wants to be leaving their house in ניסן Nisan either, right? You
know, what is it? April showers bring May flowers or something? I
mean right now it's פורים. Purim. So you know, it rains sometimes
in the spring also. So I don't know what they would say
there. So therefore what would they say? תשרי? Tishrei? I mean, is
תשרי Tishrei any better? But I guess they would say there's no
absolute rule. You know, you have to look in each locale what
the context is and what's assumed based on when you say a
year. Now the other thing you might want to look at is
how much money was paid. And that might be an indication of
what was meant, right? And this becomes a question. According to the
approach that ניסן Nisan always defines the end of the year, what
if the amount that's paid is completely out of whack? It was
ראש חודש אדר Rosh Chodesh Adar and it was a year's worth
of rent, right? Would you really say that it stops at ניסן?
Nisan? So תוספות, Tosafot, look at תוספות, Tosafot, he says אלו שנה,
Alu shanah, says תוספות, Tosafot, ולא אמרינן הדמים מודיעים. V'lo amrinan hadamim
modiyim.
And we don't say that we are going to look at the
amount that's being paid and we're going to use that to determine.
הרי הוא מתנה או פקדון. Harei hu matana o pikadon. What do
you do with all the excess funds? It's crazy. You know, he
paid ten thousand dollars for one month. So, oh, we'll either say
that was a מתנה, matana, meaning basically yeah, he overpaid and he
just wanted to give it as a gift, a signing bonus I
guess in the opposite direction. I don't know. Anyway. Or no, he
just meant it as like, hold on to this money, but he
was going to get it back in the end. Obviously there's a
big difference, which is how am I going to get the excess
money back? But that becomes also the whole fascinating question of דיני
ממונות dinei mammonos and do you go after רוב rov and what
type of factors do you use? So you know, the fact that
it's only a יש אומרים Yeish Omrim is good because it makes
more sense that there isn't a very well-defined convention, you know, that
you would use the, that you would look at the more context
to try to determine what was meant. Okay, now we are finally
done with our משנה, Mishnah, with explore, I mean with the issues
about ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah about ניסן. Nisan. Right? We so we
had מלכים, melachim, we had רגלים, regalim right?
And that's it in our משנה. Mishnah. We looked at a ברייתא
braisa that had ניסן Nisan for a whole other series of things,
עיבורים iburim etc., etc. We looked at other things that weren't in
our משנה, Mishnah, you know, חודשים chodashim and so on. And now
we're done with ניסן. Nisan. And now we move on to the
next part of the משנה Mishnah which is אייר. Iyar. Okay, which
is, right, I'm sorry, not אייר. Iyar. באחד באלול, B'echad b'Elul, thank
you, ראש השנה למעשר בהמה. Rosh Hashanah l'ma'aser behema. רבי אלעזר ורבי
שמעון אומרים באחד בתשרי. Rabbi Elazar v'Rabbi Shimon omrim b'echad b'Tishrei. Okay,
so this is when you count, you look at all the animals
born that year and you take, you know, every tenth one and
that becomes מעשר. ma'aser. And what year means born that year? And
this is the debate of whether you go by אלול Elul? or
תשרי. Tishrei. Yes? Okay. So let's take a look at the גמרא.
באחד באלול ראש השנה למעשר בהמה. B'echad b'Elul Rosh Hashanah l'ma'aser behema.
מני? Manni? So
we know רבי אלעזר ורבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar v'Rabbi Shimon say you
go by אייר. Iyar. I mean, sorry, by תשרי. Tishrei. I don't
know why I keep saying אייר. We know they say תשרי. Tishrei.
That's the next line in the משנה. Mishnah. Who is the סתם
stam author of the משנה Mishnah that says that מעשר בהמה ma'aser
behema goes by אלול? Elul So the גמרא says רבי מאיר היא.
Rabbi Meir hi. It's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. דתנן, D'tnan, we taught
in a משנה, Mishnah,
רבי מאיר אומר באחד באלול ראש השנה Rabbi Meir omer b'echad b'Elul
Rosh Hashanah the... okay... ראש השנה למעשר בהמה. Rosh Hashanah l'ma'aser behema.
Okay, so רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is the one that says the
first of אלול Elul is ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah for מעשר בהמה.
ma'aser behema. Good. So that line in the משנה Mishnah of the
first of אלול is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. ולרגלים מני? U'l'regalim manni?
Now, the גמרא said that תשרי Tishrei was ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
for רגלים. We said what does that mean? We assumed it meant
that you had to do the רגלים in order starting with פסח
in order to be over on בל תאחר. Now, who was that
author? Remember we mentioned a ברייתא braisa that had many different opinions
about
what you need about which רגלים and how many... Who was the
one that said it was three רגלים *Regalim* starting with ניסן *Nissan*?
רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*. So we saw in an earlier ברייתא *braita*
that that was רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*. אימא סיפא *Eima seifa*, now
let's look at the next line in the משנה *Mishnah*. רבי אליעזר
רבי שמעון אומרים באחד בתשרי *Rabbi Eliezer Rabbi Shimon omrim be'echad b'Tishrei*,
the first of תשרי *Tishrei*.
So the גמרא *Gemara* makes a very good question, right? The משנה
*Mishnah* says ניסן *Nissan* is ראש השנה לרגלים *Rosh Hashanah l'Regalim*,
which means basically you need כסדרן *k'sidrun* for בל תאחר *Bal Te'acher*,
right,
starting with פסח *Pesach*, right? That's what ראש השנה לרגלים *Rosh Hashanah
l'Regalim* means. And we know that that idea of בל תאחר *Bal
Te'acher* is רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*. Okay, then we say אלול למעשר
בהמה *Elul l'ma'aser behemah*
and we know from a משנה *Mishnah* in בכורות *Bechorot* that who
says that? רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. And then it says רבי שמעון
ורבי אליעזר אומרים *Rabbi Shimon v'Rabbi Eliezer omrim*, it is not אלול
*Elul* but it is תשרי *Tishrei*. Okay,
so look at our משנה *Mishnah*. First it quotes the סתם *stam*
of רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, then it shifts to the סתם *stam*
of רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, right?
So what's the story and then goes back to a רבי שמעון
*Rabbi Shimon* position? But how is it adopting a סתם *stam*, the
first line of ניסן *Nissan* is a position of a רבי שמעון
*Rabbi Shimon* position and the next line of אלול *Elul* is a
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* position? So the גמרא *Gemara* says, okay, רישא
וסיפא רבי שמעון ומציעתא
רבי מאיר *reisha v'seifa Rabbi Shimon u'mitzi'asa Rabbi Meir*. Used to be
beginning and the end is רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* and the middle
is רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*? אמר רב יוסף *Amar Rav Yosef*, רב
יוסף *Rav Yosef* says, yeah, רבי *Rebbi*! Look, רבי *Rebbi* is the
author. He gets to pick and choose. ונסיב ליה אליבא דתנאי *v'nasiv
lei aliba d'tana'i* and he picks which תנאים *Tanna'im* he likes. He
picks different positions according to different תנאים *Tanna'im*. ברגלים סבר לה כרבי
שמעון *B'Regalim savar lah k'Rabbi Shimon*, the first line of the משנה
*Mishnah* of ניסן *Nissan* and the רגלים *Regalim* go in order for
בל תאחר *Bal Te'acher* is a רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* position. ובמעשר
בהמה סבר לה כרבי מאיר *U'v'ma'aser behemah savar lah k'Rabbi Meir*, and
the next line of the first of אלול *Elul* is a רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* position, and he likes that רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*
position. So yeah, it's true that they're different authors, but that's the
way רבי *Rebbi* פסקן *paskin*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, one minute,
אי הכי *ee hachi*, if that's true, ארבע *arba*? What do you
mean four ראשי שנה *Roshei Hashanah*? חמישה הוי *Chamisha havei*, there are
five. Why are there five? Because it says, remember, it said ניסן
*Nissan* was ראש השנה למלכים *Rosh Hashanah l'melachim*, right, ולרגלים *u'l'Regalim*, okay,
and then it said אלול *Elul* and then what was next? תשרי
*Tishrei* is whatever
all the things that תשרי *Tishrei* are for. What were some of
the things mentioned in the משנה *Mishnah* for תשרי *Tishrei*? ראש השנה
לשנים ולשמיטין *Rosh Hashanah lashanim v'lishmittin*
etc., שנים ולשמיטין *shanim
v'lishmittin* etc.
And then it had שבט *Shevat*, right, for
that's for trees, ט"ו בשבט *Tu B'Shevat* etc. Okay, so we say
one, two, right, one, two, three, four. But now we've got a
problem, which you could have asked without this whole רבי שמעון *Rabbi
Shimon*, רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* thing, which is since this is ראש
השנה למלכים *Rosh Hashanah l'melachim*, this is ניסן *Nissan* 1.
לרגלים *L'Regalim* is ניסן *Nissan* 15.
So really there are one, two, three, four, five. Okay, so let's
take a look at how we're going to deal with that. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says there are five. אמר רבא *Amar Rava*, says
רבא *Rava*, ארבעה לדברי הכל *arba l'divrei hakol*,
everybody agrees to four. רבי מאיר ארבעה דל רגלים *Rabbi Meir arba
dal Regalim*, רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* would have four minus the רגלים
*Regalim*. ורבי שמעון ארבעה דל מעשר בהמה *V'Rabbi Shimon arba dal ma'aser
behemah*, רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* would have four because he would drop
מעשר בהמה *ma'aser behemah*. What does this mean? It means רבי מאיר
*Rabbi Meir* doesn't hold of this idea of רגלים *Regalim*, right, this
is a רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* position, right, that you go, start
by פסח *Pesach* and go forward. So according to רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir*, רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* wouldn't hold of this and he would
hold of four. He would have just one ניסן *Nissan* for kings,
then אלול *Elul*, then תשרי *Tishrei*, then שבט *Shevat*. So he has
four. רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* also has four. Why? רבי שמעון *Rabbi
Shimon* holds of one ניסן *Nissan*, fifteen ניסן *Nissan*, but he doesn't
hold of אלול *Elul*, because he holds מעשר בהמה *ma'aser behemah* is
תשרי *Tishrei*. So he has one ניסן *Nissan*, fifteen ניסן *Nissan*, not
אלול *Elul*, תשרי *Tishrei* and שבט *Shevat*. So both רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir* and רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* individually hold four, although רבי *Rebbi*'s
פסק *psak* gets him five, because רבי *Rebbi* now has פסקן *paskin*
one ניסן *Nissan*, fifteen ניסן *Nissan*, אלול *Elul*, תשרי *Tishrei*, שבט *Shevat*.
So the individual תנאים *Tanna'im* hold four, but by him picking and
choosing he's left with five. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר ארבעה חדשים
ובהם כמה ראשי חדשים *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar arba chodashim u'vahem
kama roshei chodashim*. Nah, four, there are four months and some of
the months have more than one ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah* like ניסן
*Nissan* is one and fifteen, but it only counts as one. When
we say four, we mean four months. All right, so מתיבי *meitvei*.
Now I'll ask you, because now it seems like there's more than
four,
even more. שישה עשר בניסן ראש השנה לעומר *Shisha asar b'Nissan Rosh
Hashanah l'omer*. The sixteenth of ניסן *Nissan* is the ראש השנה לעומר
*Rosh Hashanah l'omer*. Now what does it mean ראש השנה לעומר *Rosh
Hashanah l'omer*? It's the day you bring the עומר *omer*, but no,
it's also starts the year when you can eat the new grain.
So this is the new year for the grain that can be
eaten. שישה בסיון *Shisha b'Sivan*, the sixth of סיון *Sivan*, meaning whenever
שבועות *Shavuot* falls out, ראש השנה לשתי הלחם *Rosh Hashanah l'shtei halechem*
is ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah* for the שתי הלחם *shtei halechem* that
are brought on שבועות *Shavuot*. Now what does that mean, the קרבן
*korban*? No, because what are you allowed to do after you bring
the שתי הלחם *shtei halechem*? You know. bring the מנחה *Mincha* offerings
from the new grain.
So
in terms of it's a year of now eating of the grain
of last year's grain that starts your eating of it starts on
the sixteenth of ניסן *Nisan*, the temple's acceptance of it, you know,
having it as a sacrifice starts on the sixth of סיון *Sivan*.
So, therefore, these are two more new years. So we should have
now six or seven. So לרווחא דשיתא *l'ruvcha d'shisha* for Rava's idea
who said who basically counted
mid-days of the month as separate ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah*, we should
go from four to six. רב נחמן בר יצחק לדידיה חמישה *Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak l'didei chamisha*, and even for Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak,
he should have five. Why? Because רב נחמן בר יצחק *Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak* doesn't count mid-days separately. So the sixteenth of ניסן *Nisan*
wouldn't get counted, right? Because that's part of the ניסן *Nisan* category
of months. But סיון *Sivan* should still be counted. So how come
this idea of ניסן *Nisan* and סיון *Sivan* of the עומר *Omer*
and the שתי הלחם *Shtei HaLechem* does not up our numbers to
five and six? So the גמרא *Gemara* says like this: אמר רב
פפא *Amar Rav Papa*, so now we're going to have a series
of answers. אמר רב פפא כי חשיב מידי דחייא מאורתא מידי דלא
חייא מאורתא לא קחשיב *Amar Rav Papa ki chashiv midei d'chaya m'ortsa
midei d'lo chaya m'ortsa lo kachashiv*. We're only counting things that begin
the night before, that begin at the beginning of the day. These
things, the עומר *Omer* and the שתי הלחם *Shtei HaLechem*, are brought
in the middle of the day, so they don't count. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says: הרי רגלים דלא חייא מאורתא וקחשיב *harei regalim d'lo
chaya m'ortsa v'kachashiv*. What do you mean? The רגלים *regalim* you're only
able to bring your קרבנות *korbanot* in terms of בל תאחר *bal
t'acher* in the daytime. That doesn't start the night before, and those
are being counted. So the גמרא *Gemara* says: No, כיון דצריך לאתויי
מעיקרא *keivan d'tzarich l'asuye me'ikara*, since your obligation to bring the קרבנות
*korbanot* started already way earlier, מחייב וקאי *mechayav v'kai*, you're already obligated.
So the רגלים *regalim* is just when the obligation sort of is
over, you know, or has been violated, but in a sense it's
not like the whole thing began in the daytime of the רגלים
*regalim*. Alright, והרי יובל *v'harei Yovel*. How about יובל *Yovel*? That doesn't
begin on the night before. Why? Because presumably by יובל *Yovel* it's
on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, תעבירו שופר בכל ארצכם *ta'aviru shofar b'chol
artzechem*, which is understood to be ביום הכפורים *b'yom hakippurim* in the
daytime. So the יובל *Yovel* year doesn't really begin until the daytime
of יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. That doesn't get started the night before
and that's listed in our משנה *Mishnah*. וקחשיב *v'kachashiv*, and it's listed
in the משנה *Mishnah*. רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה
היא *Rabbi Yishmael b'no shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka hi*. No, this
is the position of רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* the son of רבי
יוחנן בן ברוקה *Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka*, דאמר *d'amar* who says: מראש
השנה חייא יובל *me'Rosh Hashanah chaya Yovel*. Although you blow the שופר
*shofar* on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, it really begins on ראש השנה
*Rosh Hashanah* and the night of ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah*. Okay, so
one answer why we didn't count sixteenth of ניסן *Nisan* and the
sixth of סיון *Sivan*, because we don't count things that start in
the middle of the day. רב ששת בריה דרב אידי אמר *Rav
Sheshet brei d'Rav Idi amar*: כי קחשיב מידי דלא תלי במעשה *ki
kachashiv midei d'lo tali b'ma'aseh*. This is maybe a simpler answer. We're
only in the משנה *Mishnah* is only mentioning things that don't require
an action, happen automatically. First of ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah* rolls around,
these הלכות *halakhot*, first of ניסן *Nisan*, these הלכות *halakhot*. מידי דתלי
במעשה *midei d'tali b'ma'aseh*, this is less about the date, this is
more about doing an action. Bringing the עומר *Omer*, bringing the שתי
הלחם *Shtei HaLechem*.
So there it's a very different type of a category, right? That
makes a lot of sense. If I said that to you, you
would tell me: It's not about being the sixteenth of ניסן *Nisan*,
it's about the fact that you bring the עומר *Omer*. And that's
what he's saying. The משנה *Mishnah* mentions things that are really about
the date and happen automatically. We're not mentioning things that are dependent
on doing an action. So the גמרא *Gemara* says: הרי רגלים מידי
דתלי במעשה וקחשיב *harei regalim midei d'tali b'ma'aseh v'kachashiv*. How about the
רגלים *regalim*? That's about an action, that's about bringing קרבנות *korbanot*. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says: No, no, it's about not doing it. The
גמרא *Gemara* says: בל תאחר ממילא חייא *bal t'acher mimela chaya*. No,
the idea of the רגלים *regalim* is because you didn't do something,
the date holds you liable. But it's not that the date has
significance because you did something on that day. Okay, and we'll just
read one more line. והרי יובל *v'harei Yovel*. How about יובל *Yovel*,
that also has a blowing of a שופר *shofar*, that's about an
action. רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה היא *Rabbi Yishmael
b'no shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka hi*. No, again, that's the idea
that it starts on ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah*. רב אשי אמר *Rav
Ashi amar*, last answer: ארבעה ראשי שנים הם שהן בארבעה ראשי חדשים
*arba'ah Roshei Hashanim hen shehen b'arba'ah Roshei Chadashim*. Okay, there are four
ראשי שנים *Roshei Hashanim* that fall on ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh*. Meaning,
we're only counting the ראשי שנה *Roshei Hashanah* that fall on the
first of the month. So we're not counting the sixteenth of ניסן
*Nisan*, we're not counting the sixth of סיון *Sivan*, we're not gonna
count the רגלים *regalim* again, because we're mentioning the רגלים *regalim* as
a whole, but we're only counting ראשי שנה *Roshei Hashanah* that begin
on the first of the month. So that's great. One, two, three,
four, all these begin on the first of the month. Except טו
בשבט *Tu B'Shevat* according to בית הלל *Beit Hillel* is טו בשבט
*Tu B'Shevat*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says: באחד
בשבט כבית שמאי *b'echad biShevat k'Beit
Shammai*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says: What do you mean? How about
the fact that באחד בשבט *b'echad biShevat* is בית שמאי *Beit Shammai*?
הכי קאמר שלושה דברי הכל *hachi ka'amar sheloshah divrei hakol*, שלושה לדברי
הכל *sheloshah l'divrei hakol*.
There are three ראשי שנה *Roshei Hashanah* according to everyone that start
on the first of the month. באחד בשבט מחלוקת בית שמאי ובית
הלל *b'echad biShevat machloket Beit Shammai v'Beit Hillel*. When it comes to
the first of שבט *Shevat*, that's a debate. So the idea that
there are four is really only a בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* position.
Okay, but anyway, again, trying to figure out how you get only
four and what you do with these other ways of counting.